<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Seminars | STAT LAB</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/</link><atom:link href="https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Seminars</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://statlab905.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Seminars</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/</link></image><item><title>Seminar on Optimization Algorithms</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/2024opt/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/2024opt/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This seminar provides a comprehensive overview of optimization algorithms, covering both theoretical foundations and practical applications. We begin with advanced convex programming techniques, including the Alternating Direction Method with Gaussian Back Substitution and optimally linearized ADMM. The seminar then explores modern optimization methods such as Adam and generalized primal–dual hybrid gradient approaches for saddle point problems. We also discuss communication-efficient statistical estimation and the balanced augmented Lagrangian method. Further topics include the global linear convergence of ADMM with multi-block variables, decentralized consensus optimization via the EXTRA algorithm, and stochastic gradient descent with variance reduction. Finally, we examine the role of optimization in double descent and investigate why overparameterized neural networks can still generalize effectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Time: 2:00pm-4:00pm, Thursday, 2024 Spring&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Location: USTC the 5th Teaching Building and Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="learning-materials">Learning Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1_YuJshk_oS3AcFjk7sIMuA?pwd=9uhs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Statistical Computing with Python</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/python/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/python/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This seminar offers a comprehensive exploration of statistical computing using Python, starting with fundamental Python programming and progressing into deep learning and optimization techniques. Topics include computer vision, image processing, and natural language processing (NLP), as well as advanced deep learning models. The seminar also introduces reinforcement learning, covering classical algorithms, Deep Q-Learning, and Policy Gradient (PG) methods, along with their practical applications. Additionally, it delves into distributed computing, providing an overview of Ray and its API for parallel deep learning and reinforcement learning with Ray RLlib. This seminar serves as a technical guide for students and researchers seeking to apply Python in statistical computing and AI-driven problem-solving.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>2023 Autumn, USTC Management Science Building and Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="learning-materials">Learning Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1MgDt-kpnB0BS28De7N8itg?pwd=4i5c" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tutorial&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1maBVF7PzLIj80ipSJRFftA?pwd=3w6u" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Video materials&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Mechanism-Fused Statistical Inference</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/mechanistic_stat/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/mechanistic_stat/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This seminar explores the fusion of mechanistic modeling and statistical inference, presenting a range of methodologies for parameter estimation, curve fitting, and uncertainty quantification. Beginning with an introduction to mechanistic models, it covers nonlinear least squares, trajectory matching, and nonparametric curve fitting with roughness penalties. Advanced topics include gradient matching, generalized profiled estimation, and local polynomial methods. We further examine equation matching techniques and sparse additive models for ordinary differential equations (ODEs). The seminar also delves into Gaussian processes and their applications in ODE modeling, culminating in a discussion on the novel use of physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) for analyzing Argo data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>2022 Autumn, USTC Management Science Building and Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1SAd9jOigvDPQhYsuPalk4Q?pwd=hky8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Deep Learning</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/dl/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/dl/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our seminar progresses from foundational concepts and text analysis to convolutional neural networks (CNNs), emphasizing image classification and optimization techniques. It explores deep learning applications in natural language processing and computer vision (object detection, semantic segmentation), followed by reinforcement learning principles. Specialized topics include methods for graph-based/non-Euclidean data and medical image analysis, providing a concise yet broad technical overview across key domains.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>2021 Summer, Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/17Jftvugz9By73c_xegzW1Q?pwd=kj8u" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Video materials&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1DsNrDT1ji7LdG2OpLEw_Jg?pwd=qpu6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Nonparametric Statistics</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/nonparametric/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/nonparametric/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our seminar consists two parts. In the first part, we cover selected topics in &amp;ldquo;Learning with Kernel&amp;rdquo;, including Loss functions, Regularization, Pattern Recognition, Implementation, Designing Kernels and Kernel Fisher Discriminant. In the second part, we report our research progress in topics of Nonparametric Statistics, including Tree methods, two sample tests on Hyperbolic Space and Change Point Detection.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Time: 7:00pm-9:00pm, Tuesday, 2022 Spring&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Location: USTC Management Science Building 1008 and Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/1kwX_9ccrDjvfWM4Rmrzw-Q?pwd=rw8v" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Optimization and Algorithm</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/optimization/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/optimization/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We cover selected topics in &amp;ldquo;Numerical Optimization&amp;rdquo;, including Line Search Method, Trust Region Method, Conjugate Gradient Method, Quasi-Newton Methods and Simplex Optimization. Besides, in the middle of the term, we listen Prof Bingsheng He from Nanjing University presenting his work on Optimization.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time-and-location">Time and Location&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Time: 7:00pm-9:00pm, Tuesday, 2022 Spring&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Location: USTC Management Science Building 1008 and Online&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="learning-materials">Learning Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/17Dq-gcn_ZsZ_XJ1_xWLmtQ?pwd=k5hy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seminar on Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/rl/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://statlab905.github.io/seminar/rl/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our seminar mainly focuses on the book &amp;ldquo;Reinforcement Learning :An Introduction&amp;rdquo;. We the basic parts of Reinforcement Learning, including Multi Armed Bandit, Thompson Sampling, Markov Decision Process, Monte Carlo Methods, Temporal-Difference Learning, On-policy Approximations and Policy Gradient Methods. We not only present the Theory of the methods in our seminar, but also use some experiment to illustrate our method.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="time">Time&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>9:30am-11:30am, Tuesday, 2022 Spring&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The materials are stored in Baidu Cloud Drive: &lt;a href="https://pan.baidu.com/s/13s5xRZo4Tt-SFNEYMLrh-Q?pwd=9qkj" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPT&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>